Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Professional correspondence-subject files
  - Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE)
    - Conferences, 1977-1980; 1986,; 1988-1996; 10 folders; national and regional (Box 39)
    - Conferences, 1997-2004; 2006-2011,; 2013; 12 folders; national and regional (Box 40)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1980; 1984,; 1988-1989,; undated (Box 41)
    - Continuing Higher Education, 1974; 1977; 2 issues; one issue contains article by Charters, "CAEO through the years" (Box 41)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1994; 10 folders (Box 41)
    - Correspondence, 1995-2013; undated; 7 folders (Box 42)
    - Directories, 1973-1980; 2001; 3 folders (Box 42)
    - "International Continuing Higher Education" report, 1990; by Shirley Hendrick, Pennsylvania State University (Box 42)
    - Newsletter, "Five Minutes with ACHE", 1983-1996; not a complete run, has gaps (Box 42)
    - Newsletter, "Five Minutes with ACHE", 1997-2013; 2 folders; not a complete run, has gaps (Box 43)
    - Rolls of past presidents and annual meetings, 1986; 1995-1996 (Box 43)
    - Strategic Plan Committee, 2004 (Box 43)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 43)
  - Association for Higher Education (AHE)
    - Conference, 1959; 1965; 3 folders; includes typescript of Charters paper, "Pressures on Higher Education for Adult Education Services" (ANC 13) (Box 43)
    - Correspondence, 1953; 1956-1957,; 1964-1966,; undated; includes a few newsletters (Box 44)
  - Association Mexicana de educacion continua (AMEC), 1991; memorabilia (nametag, certificate) (Box 44)
  - Association for Recurrent Education (ARE), 1979; policy document, "Towards a new education act" (Box 44)
  - Association of Teacher Educators (ATE), 2000-2004; newsletters (Box 44)
  - Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC)
    - Aims and objectives, 1960; undated (Box 44)
    - Committees, 1954-1963; 1971-1972; includes list of directors (Box 44)
    - Conferences, 1947; 1949-1961,; 1963-1965; 17 folders (Box 44)
    - Conferences, 1966; 1972-1973; 3 folders (Box 45)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1951; 1953,; 1956,; 1961 (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1963; 8 folders (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1968; 1973,; undated; 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Directories, 1963-1965; 1972-1974; includes a "home and spouses directory" (Box 46)
    - Ghana Study Tour, 1965; notes by Charters on his trip to Ghana, for AUEC newsletter article (Box 46)
    - List of member institutions, undated (Box 46)
    - Newsletter, 1953; 1955-1958,; 1966,; 1970,; 1973 (Box 46)
    - NUEA (National University Extension Association) Joint Committee, 1958; 1962 (Box 46)
    - Policies and procedures, circa 1958 (Box 46)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, 1953; 1956,; 1961,; 1967,; undated; informational brochures, fliers, reports from AUEC as well as other related organizations (Box 46)
    - Regional organizations (Box 47)
    - Reports and papers
      - By author, A-H, 1962-1964; undated (Box 47)
        Byrne, "Some principles of evaluation"; Emery, "Evaluating dated credits"; Golden, "Significant issues which labor must face in society"; Haygood, "The impact of urbanization on university extension"; Horn, "Promoting high standards of professional excellence"
      - By author, Knox, 1965; undated (Box 47)
        with Sjogren, "Research on adult learning: Implications for design of effective learning experiences for adults"; "Adult education research arrangements within university adult education divisions"; with Sjogren, "Achievement and withdrawal in university adult education classes"; "Adult education agency clientele analysis"; "Research and the adult educator"
      - By author, L-W, 1961; 1963,; undated (Box 47)
        McMahon, "Memorandum on AUEC address of President Francis H. Horn"; Perry, "When is education liberal?"; Siegle, "Counseling in the evening college"; Suttles, "Some facets of an evening student personnel program in an urban institution"; Thomas, untitled adult education article on illiteracy; Liveright, comments on Thomas article; Winters, "Cooperating with other groups: An address to the AUEC"
      - Unknown author, 1995; 1958,; 1960,; 1962,; undated (Box 47)
        President's message; intro, "Innovation and stability," to unidentified book; Evaluating the evening college as a teaching institution; Report of the University of Wyoming's Division of Adult Education and Community Service; Report of a conference of representatives of national organizations and agencies with a primary adult education function; University of Washington adult student rating of teacher effectiveness; Summary technical report [on] work-study conference on new educational media for NUEA; Proposal for coordinating council study of a master plan for adult education in California; Interim statement of policy for university extension [at University of California; Statement on differentiation of function [at University of California]
    - Who's Who in the Association of University Evening Colleges, 1951; booklet with brief bios of members (Box 47)
  - Association for World Education, 1996; one issue of the Journal of World Education (Box 47)
  - Australia trip, 1972-1979; See UNESCO: National Commissions: Australia.
  - Australian National University, 1964; 1973,; 1977-1978,; 1996 (Box 47)
  - Australian Studies Association of North American (ASANA), 1992; 1997,; undated (Box 47)
  - Automated Beverage Control (ABC)
    - An Automated Management Information System for Marine Corps Clubs and Recreation, 1980; unsolicited proposal (Box 47)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1986; includes note by Charters that the project was never made operational; correspondence with and about Kenneth A. Lill (chairman) and Albert G. Barnes (Executive Vice-President) (Box 47)
    - Project file, org chart, notes, memoranda, statement of work, drafts of project structure, etc. (Box 47)
    - Resumes, includes Kenneth Lill and Albert Barnes (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1980 (Box 47)
  - Axford, Roger, 1964-1965; 1977,; 1980-1984; includes c.v. (Box 48)
  - A, miscellaneous (Box 48)
  - Barnes, Albert G, 1976; 1980,; 1982; Automated assessment audits for management education (US Marine Corps); Defining sufficient futures for a humanistic learning society through androgogical reorientation (Delphi workshop) (Box 48)
    See also Automated Beverage Control (ABC); Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA).
  - Barrow, Nita, 1990; undated; clippings, fliers, curriculum vitae, several biographical sketches; includes text of speech about her (author unknown) and copy of brochure "A Lifetime In Service" published by the Permanent Mission of Barbados to the United Nations and highlighting her achievements (Box 48)
  - Basic Choices Inc., See Ohliger, John.
  - Bates College, 1992; 1997,; 1999,; 2005; 2 folders; printed material, most related to fund-raising (Box 48)
  - Bauer, Ronald C., See International Graduate School; International Intercultural Center; World University.
  - Beattie, Walter M. Jr., 1970; c.v. (Box 48)
  - Beese, C.W., See Purdue University.
  - Belanger, Paul, 1990; 1993-1994,; 1997-2002,; 2009-2010,; undated; includes c.v. (Box 48)
    See also UNESCO: Correspondence and UNESCO: Institute for Education, of which Belanger was director.
  - Benton, Robert, 1985; correspondence and presentation regarding Benton's book, Basic English Sentence Design (Box 48)
  - Bentti, Fredy, 1986; 1993-1995,; 1998,; 2010; includes extensive handwritten notes by ANC; photograph of Bentti and family (Box 48)
  - Bergeron, Robert, 1967; 1971-1972,; 1995; correspondence, clippings, printed material (Box 48)
  - Bergsten, Urban, 1972-1973 (Box 48)
  - Berlin Conference, 1987; conference title and organization unknown (Box 48)
  - Bersch, Gretchen, 1994-1996; 2001,; 2005,; 2012-2013,; undated; includes copy of Portrait of Alaska by Simmerman, inscribed by Dr. Bersch to Dr. Charters; brochure about Bersch's "Conversations on Lifelong Learning" series (Box 49)
  - Bertelsen, Paul, 1966-1978; 1981-1984,; 1987-1992; Lomnava Institute, Ghana (Box 49)
    See also International Handbook of Resources for Educators of Adults.
  - Bethune, Mary Mcleod, See Black Women's Institute.
  - Bibliographies and lists, compiled by ANC at various times
    - Adult education newsletters, [formerly Adult Education Associations Directory] (Box 49)
    - Adult education organizations [alternate title: Adult Education Associations Directory] (Box 49)
    - Adult education publications (Box 49)
    - Adult education, general, 1974; 1993 (Box 49)
  - Black Women's Institute, 1974; relates to Mary McLeod Bethune Memorial Dedication (Box 49)
  - Blakely, Robert J. and Alta
    - Correspondence, 1969-1983; 1994-1995,; 1998,; 2005; includes "Eulogy for Mrs. Hazel Hunt" by Blakely (Box 49)
    - Interview with, by James C. Hall, 1973; typescript (Box 49)
    - Resume, photograph, photo signed and inscribed to ANC (Box 49)
    - Writings, Adult education and education public broadcasting in the US (1979); Notes from the darkroom (1976); The new environment: Questions for adult educators; family genealogy/history (1972); What is adult education? (1960) (Box 49)
  - Blumberg, Art, 1972; includes survey results on faculty perceptions and attitudes, unidentified university (Box 49)
  - Boucouvalas, Marcie, 1976; 1986,; 1991-1997,; 2011,; undated; includes papers: Toward a conceptualization of international adult education: Some preliminary thoughts and reflections (1986); The transcultural self: an issue area for comparative adult education research (1991); The Greek struggle for national independence from Turkish occupation; PowerPoint on the role of the UN and UNESCO in the adult learning movement (Box 49)
    See also International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE), in which Boucouvalas was very active.
  - Bourn, C. J., 1978-1979; University of Leicester (Box 49)
  - Bown, Lalage, 1964-1968; 1971,; 1975-1977,; 1990-1992; University of Zambia (Box 50)
    See also World Conference on Comparative Adult Education: Background paper.
  - Bradley, Allan P., See Terminal education needs of Syracuse youth.
  - Brazil, See Ministério da educação e cultura, Movimento brasiliero de alfabetização.
  - Brigham Young University (BYU), 1975; 1983,; 1996; publication on 75th anniversary of their Division of Continuing Education (Box 50)
  - Brightman, Sam, 1974; 1978,; 1983-1992,; undated; includes copy of his paper, "Adult education for civic literacy"; also clippings, photographs, and other items relating to his visits to Syracuse and Cape Cod (Box 50)
  - Bron, Michal and Agnieska, 1978; 1983,; 1985,; 1987,; 1989,; 1995,; 2006-2008,; undated; mostly writings by Bron; includes abstract, table of contents, and last chapter of monograph, "Workers and post-secondary education: A cross-polity perspective"; two Uppsala Reports (no 18 and no 22) on education in Yugoslavia and Poland (Box 50)
  - Budnick, Austin, 1976; 1980; includes proposal, "Padua: An alternative education learning community for older adults" (Box 50)
  - Bureau Europeén de l'education populaire, 1983; 1986; See European Bureau of Adult Education.
  - Buttedahl, Paz G., 1977; undated (Box 50)
  - B, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Calvert, Steven L., 1986; Dartmouth Alumni Continuing Education
  - Campbell, Duncan, 1966; 1973,; 1976-1977; University of Alberta (Box 50)
  - Canadian Association for Adult Education (CAAE)
    - Committee on Non-credit University Extension, 1957; 1959 (Box 50)
    - Constitution, 1951 (Box 50)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1963; 1966,; 1981-1982,; 1984,; 1990 (Box 50)
    - Printed material, 1943; 1947,; 1964,; 1975,; undated; manifesto, conference program (1947), promotional brochures, etc. (Box 50)
  - Canadian Association of Directors of Extension and Summer Schools (CADESS), See Canadian Association for University Continuing Education (CAUCE).
  - Canadian Association for the Study of Adult Education (CASAE), 1982; 1984,; 1991,; 2000,; 2004 (Box 51)
  - Canadian Association for University Continuing Education (CAUCE), 1966; 1983-1985,; 1996; 2 folders; successor organization to CADESS; correspondence, reports, "An overview of continuing education policies and practices in Canadian universities," 2 editions; Professional Development Inventory, 1984 (Box 51)
  - Canadian Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CCPAE), 1998; list of members (Box 51)
  - Canadian Institute for Adult Education, See Institut Canadienne d'Education des Adultes (L'ICEA).
  - Carey, Liam, 1976-1980; 1983-1987; St. Patrick's College, Kildare; includes photographs from visit to Syracuse (Box 51)
  - Caribbean Regional Council for Adult Education (CARCAE), 1999; See UNESCO: Reports.
  - Carnegie Corporation, regarding funding the Center for Continuing Higher Education for Women at Syracuse University
    - Correspondence, 1963-1972; 1993,; 1998 (Box 51)
    - Proposals and reports to, circa 1960-1967; includes reports on Center for the Continuing Higher Education of Women (Box 51)
  - Cassara, Beverly, 1983; 1987,; 1991-1994,; 1996,; 1999,; undated; includes book chapter, "Participatory research: State of the art" from Materials and Methods in Continuing Education; paper, "The emerging role of women adult educators in Kenya," 1987, reprinted from Journal of Negro Education (Box 51)
  - Center for Continuing Higher Education for Women, See Carnegie Corporation.
  - Center for Adult Language Acquisition (CALA), 2008; report, "Education for adult language learners in the United States" (Box 51)
  - Center for Adult Learning and Educational Credentials (CALEC), 1998-1999; newsletters (Box 51)
  - Center for Critical Thinking, 1995; workshop catalog/promotional brochure (Box 51)
  - Center for Leadership Development, Kiev, See Chuprina, Larissa; Ukraine.
  - Center for Research on Evaluation, Standards and Student Testing (CRESST), 1994; newsletter, special issue on policy making (Box 51)
  - Center for the Study of Adult Education (CSAE), 1979-1981; See Syracuse University: Center for the Study of Adult Education (CSAE).
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA)
    See also International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE); Liveright, Alexander A. (Sandy); Schwertman, John B.; Whipple, James B.
    - Board of Directors, working papers for meetings often include reports, studies, proposals, summaries, statements, policies, etc.
      - Meetings, 1957-1960; 4 folders (Box 51)
      - Meetings, 1961-1966; 12 folders (Box 52)
      - Meetings, 1967; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Bylaws (Box 53)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1961; 8 folders (Box 53)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1968; 7 folders (Box 54)
    - Course descriptions, Nov 1951 (Box 54)
    - Evaluation of liberal adult education, project undertaken by CSLEA
      - Agenda, background, etc., 1958; undated (Box 54)
      - Interim report, complete, Sep 1958 (Box 54)
      - Interim report, partial, Sep 1958 (Box 54)
      - Conference report, Princeton, Sep 1958; content appears to be same as interim report, just in different format (Box 54)
      - Interim report, 1959 (Box 55)
      - Working papers, Jan 1960 (Box 55)
      - Summary, 1961 (Box 55)
    - Histories of
      - CSLEA: A History (Whipple), Oct 1966; 2 copies (Box 55)
      - CSLEA: A History (Whipple), Mar 1967; 2 copies (Box 55)
      - Historical Perspectives of CSLEA (Charters), 1958-1960; titles and TOCs only; most of these documents are available in the SUPCE collection (Box 55)
    - Institutes in Liberal Studies for University Administrators, 1958-1960; descriptions of workshops offered (Box 55)
    - Leadership conference, most contain only program and roster of participants
      - 4th, "Concerns of the Dean in University Adult Education", 1956; For complete proceedings, (Box 55)
        See related collection SUPCE: REP series: REP 139, "The concerns of the dean in university adult education".
      - 5th, "Evening College and Extension Administration as a Profession", 1957; includes all conference handouts (Box 55)
      - 7th, "The Changing University", 1959; includes paper, "The changing character of the university" by Nicholas J. Demerath (Box 55)
      - 8th, "Models for the Future: New Directions in Higher Adult Education", 1960 (Box 55)
      - 10th, "Adult Education Research", 1962 (Box 55)
      - 13th, "The Einsteinian Era and Education", 1965 (Box 55)
      - 15th, "Purposes for Higher Continuing Education", 1967 (Box 55)
    - Newsletters, many gaps
      - Board newsletter, 1958-1963 (Box 55)
      - Continuing Education for Adults, 1962-1967 (Box 56)
    - Policy on consultation and field work, 1966 (Box 56)
    - Printed material
      - CSLEA, brochures, fliers, etc. (Box 56)
      - Miscellaneous, other organizations, reprints of articles, brochures for programs, etc. (Box 56)
    - Proposals
      - For funds to continue the center for 15 months, 1955; agency: Fund for Adult Education (Box 56)
      - For two-year grant [to fund CSLEA], 1959; 2 folders; agency: Fund for Adult Education (Box 56)
      - To the Fund for Adult Education [to fund CSLEA], 1960 (Box 56)
      - For grant to CSLEA, 1964; agency: Carnegie Corporation (Box 56)
      - For a series of working conferences defining the role of universities in four crucial emerging areas of continuing education, 1965? (Box 56)
      - For the establishment of a National Adult Education Resources Institute and field demonstration centers, Mar 1966 (Box 56)
      - For an anthology of CSLEA publications, Nov 1966; agency: Syracuse University Press (Box 56)
      - For study of new institutional arrangements and organizational patterns for continuing education, 1966; agency: U.S. Commissioner of Education (Box 56)
      - For a new center for continuing higher education, Oct 1967 (Box 56)
      - For establishing an Institute for Comparative Study and Research in Adult Education at CSLEA, undated (Box 56)
      - For a scheduled interview study of field image of CSLEA, undated (Box 56)
    - Reports, general, filed alphabetically by title; author is given if known
      - African Adult Education Conference, Ghana (Liveright), 1962 (Box 56)
      - Audience Education project, Feb 1966 (Box 56)
      - Basutoland and the University College of Pius XII (Liveright), Jan 1962 (Box 56)
      - Degree programs especially for adults (CSLEA Memorandum #7), undated (Box 56)
      - Especially for adults, undated (Box 57)
      - Impact of urbanization on university extension (Haygood), Apr 1962 (Box 57)
      - International opportunities for lectureships, internships, scholarship, fellowships, research grants, travel grants, grants-in-aid in adult education, 1962 (Box 57)
      - International seminar on workers' and adult education, Israel (Liveright), Dec 1964 (Box 57)
      - Recent developments [on] Title I, Higher Education Act of 1965, Nov 1965 (Box 57)
      - Relations with Boston University, [1966?] (Box 57)
      - Status report on Ford Foundation grants for urban research, education and extension (Haygood), Feb 1962 (Box 57)
      - Study of adult education in the U.S. (Liveright), undated; summary and table of contents only (Box 57)
      - Studying the university's community (CSLEA Conference Report), Apr 1954; report of the National Conference on the Urban University and Community Needs, New Orleans (Box 57)
      - Summary report to the Commonwealth Fund of the Carnegie Corporation on adult education status and needs in India, southeast Asia, Australia and New Zealand (Liveright), Jun 1957 (Box 57)
      - Survey of Institutional Self-Studies (Daigneault, Foster), Jan 1961 (Box 57)
    - Reports on CSLEA, filed chronologically
      - 4th interim report (Schwertman), 1953 (Box 57)
      - 5th interim report (Schwertman), Jan 1954 (Box 57)
      - Report to the Board of Directors (Schwertman), May 1954 (Box 57)
      - 6th interim report (Schwertman), Oct 1954; 2 copies (Box 57)
      - Review of 1957, [1958?] (Box 57)
      - Summary of recommendations on future center direction (Sheats, Blake, Diekhoff, Neuffer), Nov 1958 (Box 58)
      - Salary survey, May 1959 (Box 58)
      - Analysis of Center Activities to Implement Policy, [1959-1960] (Box 58)
      - Supplement to the 1957-1958 Impact Study, [1959?] (Box 58)
      - Statement to the Fund for Adult Education about the need for, past impacts of, and future direction of the CSLEA, Jun 1960 (Box 58)
      - Statement to the Fund for Adult Education about the recommended future direction of the CSLEA, Jun 1960 (Box 58)
      - Resume of field questionnaire returns about future directions, Sep 1960 (Box 58)
      - National Seminar on Adult Education Research, Mar 1961 (Box 58)
      - Annual report, Feb 1962 (Box 58)
      - Report on examination, 1962; 1963; 2 folders; financial audits (Box 58)
      - Annual report, Jun 1965 (Box 58)
      - Semiannual report, 1966; through Dec 1965 (Box 58)
      - Outside forces operating on the field of higher adult education: Implications for the future of CSLEA, [1966?] (Box 58)
      - Consultant's Report, Aug 1967 (Box 58)
      - CSLEA in retrospect: Final report, 1968 (Box 58)
    - Special Degree Program, 1962-1963; 2 folders (Box 59)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1963; includes list of former board members (Box 59)
  - Center for War/Peace Studies, 1966; 1968 (Box 59)
  - Central New York Coalition for Adult and Continuing Education (CNYCACE)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 59)
    - Correspondence, 1990-2002; undated (Box 59)
    - Directories, 1990; 1993-1994,; 1996,; 1998,; 2001; membership directories; directory of "Providers of education and training" (Box 59)
    - Newsletters, 1991-1996; 2000-2002 (Box 59)
  - Central New York Staff Development Consortium (CNY SDC), 1998-2002; undated (Box 59)
  - Centro Europeo dell'Educazione (CEDE), 1988-1989; Maurizio Lichtner; See also Lichtner, Maurice below. (Box 59)
  - Centro Regional de Educacion Funcional en American Latina (CREFAL), 1977; 1980-1982,; 1994-1995 (Box 59)
  - Chamberlain, Martin, 1965; 1968,; 1972-1973,; 1977,; 1991-1992 (Box 59)
  - Chang, Weiwen, 2002-2003; includes paper, "Dealing with culture: Methodology for a comparative study in the United States and Taiwan" (Box 59)
  - Charter schools, 1998-1999; mostly about charter schools in New York (Box 60)
  - Charters, Jessie
    - Articles about, 1920s; 1992,; 1993,; undated; material from the 1920s are photocopies; articles, "Jessie Alan Charters: A voice for our times" (Karlovic) and "Dr. Jessie A. Charters: Reclaiming her role in adult education (Geyer) (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1964; 1991-1994; with and about (Box 60)
      See also related collection,
      Jessie and W. W. Charters Papers
      .
  - Chautauqua
    - Correspondence, 1965-1968; 1982-1989,; 1990-2009; 5 folders (Box 60)
    - Financial reports, 1964-1967 (Box 60)
    - Reports, 1964-1965; 1978; reports and recommendations; annual report (1978) (Box 61)
  - Children's Theater Program, Syracuse, 1973; proposal for theater program for jr. high students from disadvantaged areas (Box 61)
  - Childs, Gayle, See New Perspectives in University Correspondence Study, by Gayle Childs and Charles Wedemeyer.
  - Chuprina, Larissa
    - Correspondence, 1998-2001; 2004,; 2007; includes photograph (Box 61)
    - Writings (Box 61)